<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Josh Duff .com]]></title><description><![CDATA[Josh Duff .com]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 21:15:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://joshduff.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>720</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[My accomplishment for the day: a MySQL quine!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>"<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quine_%28computing%29">Quine</a>:" a program that outputs it's complete source code when run.</p>
<p>I was lounging around in the MySQL chat room on irc.freenode.net, and someone suggested that I try to write a MySQL quine - a database query that would return the text of the query itself.</p>
<p>After about half an hour of screwing around, I got it!  It may not be a fantastic achievement, but I feel pretty leet about writing my first quine in a database query language.</p>
<pre lang="mysql">
SELECT REPLACE(@v:='SELECT REPLACE(@v:=\'2\',1+1,REPLACE(REPLACE(@v,\'\\\\\',\'\\\\\\\\\'),\'\\\'\',\'\\\\\\\'\'));',1+1,REPLACE(REPLACE(@v,'\\','\\\\'),'\'','\\\''));
</pre>
<p>Only 167 characters.  Hah!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2008-11-29-my-accomplishment-for-the-day-a-mysql-quine.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2008-11-29-my-accomplishment-for-the-day-a-mysql-quine.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2008 12:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Running my first campaign!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Less than a year ago, I jumped off the high-board of nerdiness into the deep end of the role-playing pool - and ran my very first campaign.</p>
<p>I wanted a fun campaign (duh) with rules and story that would be hard for me to mess up.  For most of the campaign, the only players were two good friends with solid role-playing experience, so I was able to rely on the players to contribute a good amount of quality.</p>
<h1 id="the-story">The story</h1>
<p>I took a stab at running an old-west campaign, borrowing every western-movie trope I could think of.  The PCs played <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TheGunslinger">gunslinging</a> lawmen for hire, riding into a town oppressed by a gang of n'er-do-wells populated with plenty of tobacco-spitting, expendable, no-good <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/Outlaw">outlaws</a> to gun down.</p>
<p>Without going into too much detail: the players cleaned out a counterfeiting operation in an old widow's basement, were recruited to clean up the town, used aggressive negotiations to get rid of gang members harassing the mayor's house, and stopped another group of enforcers who were coercing money from some water-starved farmers.</p>
<p>Back in town, they took over the town prison, had a gun fight in a booby-trapped house, escaped just as it blew sky high, confronted the aristocratic gang leader on the porch of his ranch house, and finished with a gun battle on main street.</p>
<h1 id="the-system">The system</h1>
<p>At the recommendation of an experienced GM, I used the <a href="http://error420.com/documents/Boot%20Hill%202nd%20Edition.pdf">Boot Hill (second edition) rules</a>, a creation of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Gygax">Gary Gygax</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Blume">Brian Blume</a>.</p>
<p>I was looking for super-lightweight rules, so I didn't even use the full rules set described by the Boot Hill book - the only dice rolling during the campaign happened during combat.  Boot Hill gun combat is simple:</p>
<ul>
<li>The fastest draw (based on weapon speed and personal speed) goes first</li>
<li>Roll percentile dice (based on your weapon, personal accuracy, and a relatively short list of modifiers) to see if you hit:</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/images/hit-determination-chart.jpg" alt="&quot;Boot Hill hit determination chart&quot;" title="Boot Hill hit determination chart"></p>
<ul>
<li>Roll percentile dice on a wound chart to see where you hit:</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/images/wound-chart.jpg" alt="&quot;Boot Hill wound chart&quot;" title="Boot Hill wound chart"></p>
<p>Mortal wounds kill you.</p>
<p>Any wound at all gives you a -5% chance at getting to shoot first, and also to hitting the other guy.</p>
<p>Once your strength drops below 50% of what it is normally (which can often be done with a single serious wound), you start getting -20% to shooting first, and hitting.</p>
<p>It's a simple system, but one that facilitates characters dying pretty often.  A couple good rolls, and a single shot can permanently take out any character - even if he just rolled into town with a new bandanna and a pocket full of hit points.</p>
<h2 id="wait-easy-character-death">Wait, easy character death?</h2>
<p>I wanted my players to enjoy a good old-fashioned movie version of the wild west.  They were supposed to play the heroes - the guys who go flying through bar windows and come up swinging!</p>
<p>I wanted quick and dirty combat, but I wanted my PCs to be a bit more survivable.  I tried a few things to counteract the cheapness of life:</p>
<h3 id="giving-the-pcs-slightly-better-stats">Giving the PCs slightly better stats</h3>
<p>Standard nerfing - most of my NPCs would drop below half strength after one serious wound (which severely limits a character for the rest of the combat).  The player characters could took at least two (non-mortal) wounds before things got really sticky.</p>
<h3 id="making-healing-much-more-trivial-than-the-rules-suggested">Making healing much more trivial than the rules suggested</h3>
<p>According to the rules, healing is a fairly slow process, taking days or weeks to recover from any sort of combat wound.  My player characters needed to be able to get into gun battles every few hours - they could be rejuvenated by a good night's sleep, or the restorative powers of a <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ApronMatron">kindly old lady</a>'s stew.</p>
<h3 id="adding-a-new-game-mechanic">Adding a new game mechanic</h3>
<p>I decided to take a hint from the awesome and successful video game <em>Left 4 Dead</em>.  In that universe, survivor characters who go down are immobilized, but can still fire handguns until their teammates pull them up (or the zombies fill up at the brain buffet).</p>
<p>Any time one of the PCs took mortal damage, I did something similar - instead of the characters dying, they dropped to the ground and could fire their handguns at a reduced rate.  If another player made it over to them and used a round to pull them up, that character could enter the fray with some of their strength restored.</p>
<p>It wasn't a mechanic that saw a lot of use, but it turned several potential defeats into narrow victories.  I was happy with this - narrowly beating the baddies is a lot more exhilarating than seeing one side gun down the other like dogs.</p>
<h1 id="also-i-m-a-noob">Also, I'm a noob</h1>
<p>I found it a highly enjoyable experience, but there were weak spots.  The campaign was fairly light on dialog, which isn't necessarily a bad thing - I just wish I were better at having a conversation in character, and thinking on my feet.</p>
<p>My weaknesses were most evident in the final session, where my PCs held the big baddy in prison and were looking around for a way to prove his guilt (they were lawful, after all) or uncover the next plot hook.</p>
<p>I left them wandering around looking for a clue far too long before I initiated the next action for them to deal with.  They grilled the prisoner for some time (good roleplaying, at least), looking for the magic words that would advance the plot.  Blah.</p>
<h1 id="i-think-i-might-try-this-again">I think I might try this again</h1>
<p>I was very glad to have such great (and forgiving) roleplayers in my campaign.  When the GM is fresh, there's a lot less room for noobs or troublemakers.</p>
<p>I'm definitely sold on lightweight rules sets, especially when going for a more cinematic feel.  The less of a barrier there is between the players and the cool things they want their characters to do, the better.</p>
<p>I have a suspicion that we might try this (noobs GMs practicing with friends) again sometime soon - if you have any suggestions for easy-to-pick-up gaming systems, or good scenarios for some one-shot sessions, then surrender your knowledge to my gaping mind-hole!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2010-01-15-running-my-first-campaign.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2010-01-15-running-my-first-campaign.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2010 03:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Convert blocks of text to sentence case in MySQL]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>You know what I hate?  Paragraphs of capital (or all lowercase) letters.</p>
<p>The other day a coworker was looking to beautify a large quantity of data spread across some MySQL tables.  I created this function to make his life easier:</p>
<pre><code class="language-sql">DELIMITER $
CREATE FUNCTION `f_sentence_case`(strInput TEXT, nMinimumLength INT) RETURNS TEXT
DETERMINISTIC
BEGIN

    DECLARE result TEXT;
    DECLARE LastSpace INT;
    DECLARE NextSpace INT;
    DECLARE NextSlash INT;
    DECLARE Word TEXT;
    DECLARE NewSentence INT;
    DECLARE PreviousCharacter CHAR(1);
    DECLARE TrimmedWord TEXT;
    DECLARE NumberOfSpaces INT;
    DECLARE Swap INT;

    SET strInput := CONCAT(strInput, ' ');
    SET result := '';
    SET LastSpace := 1;
    SET NextSpace := LOCATE(' ', strInput, LastSpace + 1);
    SET NextSlash := LOCATE('/', strInput, LastSpace + 1);

    SET NextSpace := IF(LEAST(NextSlash, NextSpace) = 0, GREATEST(NextSlash, NextSpace), LEAST(NextSlash, NextSpace));

    label1: WHILE NextSpace DO

        SET Word := SUBSTR(strInput, LastSpace, NextSpace - LastSpace);
        SET PreviousCharacter := SUBSTR(strInput, LastSpace - 1, 1);
        SET NewSentence := LastSpace = 1 OR (NewSentence AND PreviousCharacter = ' ') OR PreviousCharacter IN('.', '!', '?');

        SET TrimmedWord := LTRIM(Word);
        SET NumberOfSpaces := LENGTH(Word) - LENGTH(TrimmedWord);
        SET Word := TrimmedWord;

        # Make it lowercase if it is all uppercase
        SET Word := IF(LENGTH(Word) &gt;= nMinimumLength AND Word NOT REGEXP '[0-9]',
            IF(NewSentence,
                CONCAT(UCASE(SUBSTR(Word, 1, 1)), LCASE(SUBSTR(Word, 2, LENGTH(Word) - 1))),
                LCASE(Word)
            ),
            Word);

        SET result := CONCAT(result, REPEAT(' ', NumberOfSpaces), Word);

        SET Swap := LastSpace;
        SET LastSpace := NextSpace;
        SET NextSpace := LOCATE(' ', strInput, Swap + 1);
        SET NextSlash := LOCATE('/', strInput, Swap + 1);
        SET NextSpace := IF(LEAST(NextSlash, NextSpace) = 0, GREATEST(NextSlash, NextSpace), LEAST(NextSlash, NextSpace));

    END WHILE label1;

RETURN result;

END$
DELIMITER ;
</code></pre>
<h1 id="what-it-does">What it does</h1>
<p>It seems to perform generally as I hoped it would; which is to say that it formats text to be sentence case.</p>
<p>More specifically, it alters all the "words" (a set of non-numeric, non-whitespace characters) that are longer than the specified minimum length.</p>
<p>It changes the words to be all lowercase, unless they happen to be the first word after a punctuation mark (in which case the first character of the word is made uppercase).</p>
<h1 id="useage">Useage</h1>
<p>To clean up a field so that it is formatted in sentence case (ignoring all words with less than 3 characters), simply run this query:</p>
<pre><code>UPDATE `table` SET `field` = f_sentence_case(`field`, 3);
</code></pre>
<p>Other than that, my only specs for the query were for it to be functional and hopefully not break my brain when I went back to read it later.  If anyone has any significant improvements to it, let me know!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2010-01-22-convert-blocks-of-text-to-sentence-case.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2010-01-22-convert-blocks-of-text-to-sentence-case.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2010 13:31:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Logical errors in queries: DO NOT WANT]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>During my career developing database-driven software (teehee, I'm a professional) I've noted that the most horrific query errors are the logical ones - queries that parse correctly, and return reasonable-looking data, but make wrong assumptions about how different parts of the query relate to each other.</p>
<p>One particular error that I've seen time and time again (even from people who have been writing queries for a while) can occur when summarizing data from multiple tables that have a one-to-many relationship.</p>
<p>...In other words, it could occur in queries written for most database-driven software.</p>
<h2 id="solution-fix-the-problem-by-writing-about-it">Solution: fix the problem by writing about it!</h2>
<p>I wrote <a href="http://wikido.isoftdata.com/index.php/The_GROUPing_pitfall">a page documenting</a> the cause of the logical error, doing my best to warn people against letting it slip into their own code.</p>
<p>I attempted to write it so it would be easy to read, possibly even entertaining (a lofty goal for a manual on writing database queries, perhaps) - there is some colorful language and plenty of juvenile humor mixed with the tech-speak.</p>
<p>The doc itself is part of the wiki of the company where I work.  I don't write a ton of documentation for our developers or customers (certainly not as much as I should), but whenever I do, I get this awesome feeling of usefulness.  Oh, and pride.  Sometimes, I feel so proud, that I feel compelled to link other people (who have no relationship to my company) to what I wrote!  Ridiculous, I know.</p>
<p>Remember: if you write queries, it is your responsibility to guarantee that they return true and accurate data!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2010-02-04-logical-errors-in-queries-do-not-want.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2010-02-04-logical-errors-in-queries-do-not-want.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2010 15:17:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Run a query for every table in a database]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Ever wished you could run a dangerous query like DROP TABLE or TRUNCATE against every table in a database in a single query?</p>
<p>No?</p>
<p>Well, how about something like CHECK or REPAIR table, then?</p>
<p>If you ever find yourself in the rare situation where you need to run the same query across every table in a database, this procedure might make your life easier:</p>
<pre><code>DELIMITER $
CREATE PROCEDURE `p_run_for_each_table`(IN strDatabase TEXT, IN strOperation TEXT)
    DETERMINISTIC
BEGIN
    DECLARE strQuery TEXT;
    DECLARE strTable VARCHAR(255);
    DECLARE bDone INT DEFAULT 0;
    DECLARE TableCursor CURSOR FOR
        SELECT `TABLE_NAME`
        FROM `information_schema`.`TABLES`
        WHERE `TABLE_SCHEMA` = strDatabase AND TABLE_TYPE = 'BASE TABLE';
    DECLARE CONTINUE HANDLER FOR NOT FOUND SET bDone = 1;

    OPEN TableCursor;

    REPEAT
        FETCH TableCursor INTO strTable;

        SET @QueryThatWasPassedIn := REPLACE(
            REPLACE(strOperation, '{?database}', strDatabase)
            , '{?table}', strTable);

        PREPARE Statement FROM @QueryThatWasPassedIn;
        EXECUTE Statement;
    UNTIL bDone END REPEAT;

    CLOSE TableCursor;
    DEALLOCATE PREPARE Statement;
END$
DELIMITER ;
</code></pre>
<h1 id="useage">Useage</h1>
<p>The procedure takes two parameters.  The first one is the name of the database whose tables you want to run the query for.</p>
<p>The second is the query you would like to run.  The strings "{?database}" and "{?table}" will be replaced with the database and table names.</p>
<pre><code>CALL p_run_for_each_table('databasename', 'SELECT * FROM {?database}.{?table}');
</code></pre>
<h1 id="what-queries-you-can-run">What queries you can run</h1>
<p>You should be able to use any queries that can be run in a prepared statement - you can find the list about two-thirds of the way down <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/sql-syntax-prepared-statements.html">this page</a>.</p>
<p>As of MySQL 5.1, you can run these queries: "<code>ALTER TABLE</code>, <code>CALL</code>, <code>COMMIT</code>, <code>CREATE INDEX</code>, <code>CREATE TABLE</code>, <code>DELETE</code>, <code>DO</code>, <code>DROP INDEX</code>, <code>DROP TABLE</code>, <code>INSERT</code>, <code>RENAME TABLE</code>, <code>REPLACE</code>, <code>SELECT</code>, <code>SET</code>, <code>UPDATE</code>, and most <code>SHOW</code> statements."</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2010-02-19-run-a-query-for-every-table-in-a-database.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2010-02-19-run-a-query-for-every-table-in-a-database.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2010 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sandwich war crimes: the Dirty Mother]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>For those attending a university, the end of a semester is a time of much rejoicing.  During my last semesters at such an institution, I took place in an end-of-year celebratory tradition involving a ridiculous sandwich.</p>
<p>In some issue of Maxim (November 2005?) there was an article featuring absurd sandwich-based foods.  So ridiculous were these edibles that some fraternity brothers of mine decided that the consumption of one such sandwich would make a fitting end-of-semester celebration.</p>
<p>I was unable to find the original article online, but found the ingredients <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101103053652/http://www.ntxalliance.com/index.php?action=printpage;topic=3970.0">here</a>.  I post them here for posterity.</p>
<h2 id="the-dirty-mother">The Dirty Mother</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>"Use two slices of buttery Texas toast as bookends, and slap together a sausage patty, hash browns, and three generous chops of ham, separating each layer with a slice of cheddar cheese. Throw two fried eggs in the mix, and comfort them with four strips of crispy bacon. A splash of ketchup or Worcestershire sauce is your choice, but tons of S&amp;P is mandatory."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We would usually go to IHOP, order the ingredients individually, and assemble the sandwiches ourselves.  The braver souls in the group would purchase fries as a side dish.</p>
<p>These memories are making me hungry.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2010-05-25-dirty-mother.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2010-05-25-dirty-mother.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 19:57:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Profanities and other funny words]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I recently did a quick audit of the source code I help maintain/develop for <a href="http://wikido.isoftdata.com/index.php/ISoft_Data_Systems">the company I work for</a>.  By which I mean, I spent the last part of a Friday searching through our code for funny words.</p>
<p>I decided to open up by looking for traditional profanities - a commonly-accepted method of gauging the state of a project (see: <a href="http://www.vidarholen.net/contents/wordcount/">profanities in the Linux kernel, graphed over time</a> and <a href="http://www.kuro5hin.org/story/2004/2/15/71552/7795">a quick look at the Win2k source</a>).</p>
<p>Below, I provide a list of my findings, with a few examples.  Enjoy a look at the source code of a functioning product with many users!</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: if any of the words that you are about to read will offend you, then don't read them.</em></p>
<h1 id="the-classics">The classics</h1>
<p>I started off by looking for looking for the current English classics:</p>
<p><strong>Fuck</strong>: 6 times.
Example:</p>
<pre><code>// If they had any unsaved changes, they're pretty much fucked, because
// this customer has apparently been modified by another screen.
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Shit</strong>: 10</p>
<pre><code>// For now, I believe that all the data is updated on the fly, so saving first is not
// necessary, but maybe we should just for shits and giggles
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Crap</strong>: 22
The expletive for the more vocabulary-sensitive programmer!</p>
<pre><code>//!!! It was late, we were tired, so I hacked this crap together !!!
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// What the crap does this button do? - I disabled it because I think that this button
// is misleading and confusing
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Hell</strong>: 1</p>
<pre><code>// If it wasn't any of the valid options, then get the hell out
</code></pre>
<h1 id="insults">Insults</h1>
<p>It's usually another programmer's fault.</p>
<p><strong>Stupid</strong>: 75
The code is stupid, the users are stupid, other developers are stupid.  According to the comments, at least.</p>
<pre><code>// Clear out year if it is a stupid number
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// Here we tell the user they are stupid when they do stupid things
// If the user forgets to specify a table, gently remind them that it's a good idea,
// then return
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// When you minimize, it tells you you're size 0 now.  That seems stupid, ignore it
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// Die, stupid message boxes
</code></pre>
<pre><code>TRACE("Stupid quickbooks.\n");
</code></pre>
<pre><code>IQBBasePtr stupid = response-&gt;GetDetail();
TRACE("Response Type: %d\n", (int)stupid-&gt;Type-&gt;GetValue());
InterpretResponse(stupid);
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// Thigs are different (stupid) without this flag.  I don't currently support its omission
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Dumb</strong>: 17</p>
<pre><code>// There was some seriously wacky code here earlier including a really dumb memory leak.
// I tested my changes and they seem to work fine, nevertheless, I wasn't able
// to fully understand what this code was attempting to do so I may have missed
// some obscure feature.
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Retarded</strong>: 4</p>
<pre><code>// Because CStrings are retarded and don't do well with binary data, we have to copy the
// data in to the query in a rather inconvenient manner.
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Idiot</strong>: 2</p>
<pre><code>// Else politely inform the user that they are an idiot
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Hack</strong>: 6</p>
<pre><code>// Look at the first part of the label to find the operation (this is a sort of
// dirty hack so that) we don't have to change the database.
</code></pre>
<h1 id="incredulity">Incredulity</h1>
<p>Really?</p>
<p><strong>Why</strong>: 84
The only word with a higher count than "stupid" - there is always more for a programmer to learn.  Or speculate on.  Or rage at.</p>
<pre><code>//!!! For some reason ODBC crashes at this point if you've already done a query !!!
//!!! I can't really figure out why !!!
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// Not sure why we would want to do bitwise operations...
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// WHy doesn't this exist?
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// I don't see why we'd do this
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// CRH asks: Why do we use Format() instead of "="? Can't we assume that it's slower?
// JDD Answers: what Formats?  What are you talking about?  You crazy, Charles!
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// Removed 2006.02.17 - This makes it so that negative balances show up positive.
// I am not sure sure why it was ever here.
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// This doesn't seem to work.  I'm not sure why
</code></pre>
<p><strong>wtf</strong>: 25
Often heard expressed verbally by developers reading code.</p>
<pre><code>catch (...)
{
    TRACE("Seriously, wtf\n");
    // sic vita est
}
</code></pre>
<pre><code>// Sort the incoming files alphabetically (windows sometimes reverses the order (wtf?)
</code></pre>
<h1 id="random">Random</h1>
<p><strong>Ridiculous</strong>: 2
When three syllables just isn't enough.</p>
<pre><code>// Make the quantity not have ridiculous decimal places
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Pants</strong>: 3</p>
<p>That's right, and all 3 times inside of a static string, too!</p>
<pre><code>strPCProductCode = GetInitSetting(__MASTERWND, "session", "productcode", "pants");
</code></pre>
<p>That fourth argument is the default value, returned if there is no existing setting with that name.  So... yeah.</p>
<p><strong>lol</strong>: 3</p>
<pre><code>// lol xor
if ((bPaid || bUnpaid) &amp;&amp; !(bPaid &amp;&amp; bUnpaid))
</code></pre>
<p><strong>lulz</strong>: 1</p>
<pre><code>// Half implemented, lulz
</code></pre>
<h1 id="a-few-other-gems">A few other gems</h1>
<pre><code>// If shift was already depressed, fo' real, don't screw that up
</code></pre>
<p>Obvious mental deterioration:</p>
<pre><code>// A grape typed this line in:
//9
</code></pre>
<p>And... uh... this was at the bottom of a header file...</p>
<pre><code>// Standardized code makes him happy!
;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
;;                        ;;
;;        ;;;;;;;;        ;;
;;       ;;      ;;       ;;
;;      ;; ;;  ;; ;;      ;;
;;      ;;        ;;      ;;
;;      ;;    ;   ;;      ;;
;;      ;;        ;;      ;;
;;      ;; ;;;;;; ;;      ;;
;;       ;;  ;;  ;;       ;;
;;        ;;;;;;;;        ;;
;;                        ;;
;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;

// Non-Standardized code makes him sad!
// And keeps him up all night, screaming
;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
;;                        ;;
;;        ;;;;;;;;        ;;
;;       ;;;    ;;;       ;;
;;      ;; /*\/*\ ;;      ;;
;;      ;; \_/\_/ ;;      ;;
;;      ;;   ^^   ;;      ;;
;;      ;; /****\ ;;      ;;
;;      ;; \****/ ;;      ;;
;;       ;;      ;;       ;;
;;        ;;;;;;;;        ;;
;;                        ;;
;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
</code></pre>
<p>8-|</p>
<h1 id="so-yeah">So, yeah...</h1>
<p>Found any entertaining metadata in code?  Link me!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2010-06-21-profanities-and-other-funny-words.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2010-06-21-profanities-and-other-funny-words.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2010 09:11:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How Should We Then Drive?]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><em>Inside joke: the title of this post is a reference to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_Should_We_Then_Live%3F">a book</a> I have never actually read</em></p>
<p>I believe that God created the world, and that those who are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limited_atonement">chosen</a> by him should obey him to the best of their abilities.  Despite these aspirations, I'm a terrible sinner.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, at least I've got goals to aspire to, right?  Sure, there are quite a few that most people don't agree with, especially <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=leviticus%2018:22&amp;amp;version=MSG">the ones that prohibit actions that non-Christians (and even many self-proclaimed Christians) don't want to call evil</a>.</p>
<p>Still, most people are on board with the second-greatest commandment - in fact, <a href="http://store.penny-arcade.com/products/pat070181">according to popular culture</a>, that is in fact the main point of Jesus' coming to Earth!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>37 Jesus said to him, "'You shall love the LORD your God with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your mind.'</p>
<p>38 This is the first and great commandment.</p>
<p>39 And the second is like it: 'You shall love your neighbor as yourself.'</p>
<p>40 On these two commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets."</p>
<p><a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matthew%2022:37-40&amp;amp;version=MSG">Matthew 22:37-40</a> (NKJV)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(And for those paying attention, yes, I consider Penny Arcade to be an arbiter of popular culture.)</p>
<p>But if I'm not engaging in weekly gay-hunts, what IS my Christianity doing for me?  Well, among the many other instructions for living life that God passed down to us, it seems that he really does care about Christians being an improvement for the quality-of-life of the people around us:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Let me tell you why you are here. You're here to be salt-seasoning that brings out the God-flavors of this earth. If you lose your saltiness, how will people taste godliness? You've lost your usefulness and will end up in the garbage." <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matthew%205:13&amp;amp;version=MSG">Matthew 5:13</a> (MSG)</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="seriously-what-is-this-post-even-about">Seriously, what is this post even about</h1>
<p>All right, so Christians aren't supposed to be assholes.  Most people sort of assume that already, even given plenty of implicit counter-arguments via the actions of Christians they know.</p>
<p>However, I've noticed a high correlation between driving a vehicle on the road and anger.  While driving as a passenger, I've noticed that it is extremely common for a driver to express anger at</p>
<ul>
<li>The drivers sharing the road with him</li>
<li>Shitty things that happen while driving (inconvenient red lights, poor road signs, etc)
The former is by far the most common - the other vehicles on the road have a tendency to cut you off, slow you down, fail to announce where they are going, and generally just act like jerks.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="why-does-that-burn-people-up-so-much">Why does that burn people up so much?</h2>
<p>If I accidentally bump my shopping cart into someone else at the grocery store, I'll quickly apologize - and the odds are that they'll say something to the effect of "ah, don't worry" or give an understanding smile, or at worst give a small huff and push on in annoyance.</p>
<p>If I turn left on a street and someone in oncoming traffic has to slow down to avoid me safely, I don't usually get a chance to hear their response.  I've driven with enough people to imagine it, though - when you see someone doing something stupid or unnecessary in a way that inconveniences you, you generally feel a quick flash of anger toward them, and may say something to that effect at their expense.</p>
<p>Maybe it's because you just see vehicles - you're not dealing with humans, you're dealing with 4 wheels and a bumper sticker pushing [political party you hate]!  Most people are polite enough to be diplomatic in the face of being inconvenienced by another human face, but if a hunk of metal cuts you off, you feel real rage at the theoretical person inside of it!</p>
<h1 id="i-m-glad-i-m-smarter-than-that">I'm glad I'm smarter than that!</h1>
<p>Oh wait, no, I get mad exactly like that, all the time.  Despite the Bible hammering in the fact that <a href="http://www.openbible.info/topics/self-control">God expects you to be working on this self-control thing</a>, I've raged at other drivers about 100% more than I should have.  What am I supposed to do, turn every driving excursion into a painful turn-the-other-cheek exercise?</p>
<p>Well, that has kind of happened - but not until after I started adopting a proactive stance towards driving smart.</p>
<p>My life was changed (no, really!) when I read <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20201109033625/http://trafficwaves.org/trafexp.html">this site</a> written by an engineer on the internet.  I'd recommend reading it over, but here's the basic premise:</p>
<ul>
<li>Busy roads (especially big ones like highways) get inefficient to travel on quite a bit</li>
<li>It turns out that if you drive in a certain way, you can make highway driving a lot more efficient... not just for yourself, but for all the people behind you, too.</li>
</ul>
<p>So how does a motivated engineer make the world better?  It turns out, you can improve the quality-of-life of those around you by simply <strong>leaving a big gap between you and the vehicle in front of you</strong>.</p>
<p>I don't want to belabor all of the points he makes (seriously, you should read his site), but the general idea is</p>
<ul>
<li>If you never hit your brakes, the people behind you never have to hit their brakes, which lets everyone avoid the burst-forward-then-come-to-nearly-a-complete-stop situation that happens way too often on busy roads</li>
<li>It's easy for people to merge in in front of you, which lets the lanes next to you avoid the someone-driving-really-slow-trying-to-merge-lanes situation</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="is-that-really-how-you-drive-like-a-christian">Is that really how you drive like a Christian?</h1>
<p>So you're leaving a carefully-engineered gap between you and the traffic in front of you.  Traffic behind you is demonstrably better because of it.  What's the big deal?</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that this habit is not natural at all.  At least not to me.  When did I turn into a competitive driver looking to beat everyone else to my exit?  I'm not sure.  Maybe it was the day I got my drivers license.  Maybe it was the day I was born with two working testicles.  I haven't been able to pin it down.</p>
<h2 id="they-just-keep-merging">They just... keep... merging!</h2>
<p>People will merge in front of you.  And man, no matter how zen I've been feeling about driving lately, my first instinct is STILL "gotta close the gap so the rest of the horde doesn't jump in in front of me!"</p>
<p>Calm yourself with these facts: each car who merges in front of you (potentially forcing you to let up on the accelerator in order to maintain good distance between you and the car ahead) adds... maybe 5 seconds to your trip.  Sure, there's a slim chance that those 5 seconds could cause you to miss a light somewhere, but aren't those low odds worth improving the driving situation for all those around you and behind you?</p>
<p>Don't forget: the easier it is for people to merge into your lane, the smoother traffic will be for all of the people behind you!</p>
<h2 id="not-dying-is-good-too">Not dying is good, too</h2>
<p>So yeah, this falls by the wayside whenever people are in a hurry, but it turns out that the more space you leave between you and the vehicle in front of you, the safer you are.</p>
<p>I'm struggling not to write a 500-word rant on this topic alone.  Two seconds to respond to sudden developments ahead of you makes a massive difference compared to one second... and protip: you've been counting seconds too fast.  Giving yourself a larger margin of error turns "accidents" into much safer near-misses.</p>
<p>But keeping your car and skull dent-free are just happy side effects that can happen when you decide to try to apply the biblical principle of making-life-better-for-others to driving.</p>
<p>Resist the power of <a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/2004/3/19/">John Gabriel's Greater Internet Fuckwad Theory</a> - start training yourself to be a blessing to the anonymized people on the road around you!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2011-09-26-how-should-we-then-drive.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2011-09-26-how-should-we-then-drive.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Writing Noddity]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Some time in 2012, I decided to write my own blogging platform in JavaScript.  I hashed out my goals with a friend over an evening.  "It'll be simple," I said.  "You'll make changes to a directory full of Markdown files, and that's your blog!  I should be able to write the prototype in one evening!"</p>
<p>If you want to read some mediocre code from early in my JavaScript career, that prototype code is <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity/commit/c91ee844b55f9cb2cfe809b9b3666536ba8cc9e7">on the internet</a>.  I was still figuring out Node best practices, and dipping my feet into functional programming.</p>
<p>It took me a surprising amount of work to write something that could replace Wordpress as my blogging platform, let alone something that somebody else could conceivably download and use.</p>
<p>This post is about the work I did to Make It Happen.</p>
<h1 id="making-up-my-mind">Making up my mind</h1>
<p>The project's specific goals didn't solidify until after I'd started writing it.  I eventually settled on:</p>
<ol>
<li>static file deployments (no server-side code, deployable on Github Pages or shared hosting)</li>
<li>no build step to turn markdown into html</li>
<li>browse to new pages without waiting for a round-trip to the server</li>
</ol>
<p>I had dream features as well, features I wish all content sites had.  Interestingly, these features all come from MediaWiki:</p>
<h2 id="an-edit-button-on-every-page">An edit button on every page</h2>
<p>I've been editing Wikipedia for years, and my first instinct when I see poor grammar or overly-long paragraphs is to click an "edit" button and fix the problem.  Sadly, most blogs don't have an edit button.</p>
<p>Everyone should be able to feel the catharsis of fixing someone else's mistakes on the internet.</p>
<h2 id="easy-linking-to-other-pages">Easy linking to other pages</h2>
<p>I shouldn't have to think about the deployment environment when I reference one of my other posts.  When I link to another post I've written, it should be by the file name, and nothing more.</p>
<p>Having to link to <code>http://mysite.com/blog/#!/my-awesome-posts/some-file.md</code> is unacceptable.  I need wiki-style <code>[link.md|linking]</code>.</p>
<h2 id="embeddable-templates">Embeddable templates</h2>
<p>This is MediaWiki/Wikipedia's killer feature.  Any page can be embedded in any other page - and since you can pass parameters to the embedded document, you can use templates to build domain-specific languages for content.</p>
<p>I dug in to MediaWiki templates a bit when administrating the <a href="http://wikido.isoftdata.com">MediaWiki documentation site for my previous employer</a>, and am totally sold on the feature.</p>
<p>I wanted all that wiki power, but without the archaic MediaWiki formatting syntax.</p>
<h1 id="work-that-other-people-did-for-me">Work that other people did for me</h1>
<ul>
<li>I planned on using Substack's <a href="http://browserify.org/">Browserify</a> as my module/build system from very early on, letting me use large chunks of client-side code in my RSS and static file servers.</li>
<li>DOM manipulation was not something I had any intention of rewriting, so I decided to try Rich Harris's sweet <a href="http://www.ractivejs.org/">RactiveJS</a> library.  Life got even awesomer when I realized that Ractive's mustache syntax would be the perfect way to allow code in embedded templates.</li>
<li>Even though the blog itself runs without any server-side code, it caches post content, and that means storage.  I wrote everything to Rod Vagg's <a href="https://github.com/rvagg/node-levelup">LevelUP</a> interface, giving me an ideal key-value store.  Noddity modules use localstorage in the browser, Redis on the RSS/static file servers, and in-memory structures in unit tests, with no code changes or storage mocks.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="why-did-that-take-so-long-to-implement">Why did that take so long to implement?</h1>
<p>Having those goals in mind, I was able to start working on the other tools that I would need to exist.</p>
<p>Astute students of practical computer science will have recognized goal #3 above as something that requires caching, one of the <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TwoHardThings.html">two hard problems</a>.</p>
<p>While it didn't occur to the me of yester-year, it should not surprise you to hear that most of the code I wrote to get Noddity running was in the caching layer.</p>
<h2 id="post-metadata">Post metadata</h2>
<p>Before I dug into the caching, I started by nailing down the post format.  I needed to formalize a big ball of http-accessible blog content.</p>
<p>I wrote <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity-retrieval">noddity-retrieval</a> to abstract away accessing a directory full of Markdown files, and <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/text-metadata-parser">text-metadata-parser</a>+<a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/weak-type-wizard">weak-type-wizard</a> to parse metadata from the top lines of my blog post files.</p>
<p>It turns out that putting metadata in plain text isn't a new thing - Jekyll's "Front Matter" has become the de-facto way to embed metadata in content files, though it was quite young when I started on Noddity.  text-metadata-parser was the implementation I wrote, which has since changed to support "Front Matter" YAML.</p>
<h2 id="caching">Caching</h2>
<p>Wheeeeeee!  This is one of those things you instinctively know that you shouldn't be re-implementing.</p>
<p>Still, I couldn't find a solution on npm (the current winner of <a href="http://www.modulecounts.com/">Having Code On The Internet</a>) that matched my goals:</p>
<ul>
<li>Return a cached value as quickly as possible, regardless of age</li>
<li>Update the cached value automatically every so often</li>
<li>Expire keys based on the last time they were requested, not the last time the value changed</li>
</ul>
<p>So, I wrote <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/levelup-cache">levelup-cache</a>, and, in what I consider my Favorite Abstraction Layer in Noddity, I wrote the <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/expire-unused-keys">expire-unused-keys</a> module to take responsibility for knowing when a key needed to be refreshed or dropped.</p>
<p>Since writing it, I've realized that expire-unused-keys is a great low-level building block in many caching solutions.  I'm kind of proud of that library.</p>
<p>Next I wrote <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity-butler">noddity-butler</a> - which combines all of the above to return parsed posts from a Noddity content directory (like <a href="http://joshduff.com/content/">joshduff.com/content</a>) as efficiently as possible.</p>
<p>The butler is used by both the client and the RSS/static servers to access a given site's content.</p>
<h2 id="the-actual-front-end">The actual front-end</h2>
<p>After assembling those parts on my nights and weekends, I made the real website.  Most of the front-end code by lines is taken up by the "recursively-embedded-posts" logic, which was not nearly as straightforward as it seemed in my head when I decided "hey, I should have embeddable templates!"</p>
<p>Eventually, I wrote <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity-renderer">noddity-renderer</a>, which will turn a Noddity blog post into either static HTML, or recursively infinite Ractive elements that automatically update themselves whenever the noddity-butler reports any changes.</p>
<p>It's, uh, an interesting library.  It turns out "static html" and "a self-updating front-end" do share code, but imply very different architectures to pull off reasonably.  If you can give me any advice on the structure of <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity-renderer/blob/master/index.js">the code</a> I'd love to hear it.</p>
<h1 id="real-web-site-features">"Real" web site features</h1>
<p>I didn't want to drop Wordpress until I had an RSS feed, and search engines could index my individual pages.</p>
<p>The RSS feed wasn't difficult, all it takes is a <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity/blob/master/index.html#L11">link element</a> pointing to the url of a server that knows how to turn querystring parameters into a feed of posts using Noddity Butler.  Hesto presto, <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/rssaas">rssaas</a>.</p>
<p>Making search engines happy with your Web 3.0 single-page app is a bit more involved - you have to add a <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity/blob/master/index.html#L13-L18">special line to your html</a> to tell the search engine spiders to visit a <a href="https://developers.google.com/webmasters/ajax-crawling/docs/specification">special querystring that you have to handle on the server</a> - in the case of Noddity by using an <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity/blob/master/.htaccess#L27-L32">.htaccess file</a> to redirect the spiders to a server capable of serving static html versions of the markdown posts.  I named that module <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/seoaas">seoaas</a>.</p>
<p>It turned out those two applications shared a lot of code, so I moved the core out to the <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/noddity-service-server">noddity-service-server</a>.  If you ever want to write a node.js server that references a remote Noddity blog, that's the library you probably want to be using.</p>
<h1 id="does-anyone-actually-want-to-use-it">Does anyone actually want to use it?</h1>
<p>I've always admired the programmers who release polished projects that others can use to solve problems with a few clicks.</p>
<p>I wanted to release a project like that - even if it is a very narrow problem set, I want you to be able to use Noddity to easily solve real problems.</p>
<p>I registered <a href="http://noddity.com">noddity.com</a>, and used the majority of a working-vacation with my wife at a bed-and-breakfast to write copy and fix bugs that I discovered in the process.</p>
<p>Cloning from github, running <code>npm install</code> + <code>npm build</code>, and deleting the leftover cruft is almost acceptable for just me, but it's not very friendly for people who want to give it a quick try.</p>
<p>So, I wrote a magical Noddity installer.  It requires typing some things into the command-line, but <a href="http://noddity.com/content/image/noddity-install.gif">not many</a>.  Install one global module from npm, and you can create a fresh Noddity project in any directory.</p>
<h1 id="a-winner-is-me">A winner is me?</h1>
<p>So I'm a Real Open Source Programmer now, I suppose!  I wrote code that other people could conceivably use to solve their own problems.  A <a href="http://davistobias.com/">few</a> of my <a href="http://tobiaslabs.com/">sexier</a> <a href="http://josephdykstra.com/">friends</a> have already deployed their own sites based on Noddity's code.</p>
<p>Noddity has some stars on Github, but I don't know how to market it.  Given how much work the most popular open source developers seem to do to support their code, I'm not 100% sure I want to.</p>
<p>But I am a selfish human with selfish human desires.  I want people to use my code because it would validate the work I put into it.</p>
<p>Plus, I get a special lift when I act as a multiplier to someone else.</p>
<p>So I want Noddity to seem usable, and painless enough to override the "it would be easier to write it myself" instinct we all feel, and solid and featured enough that people would actually consider deploying it instead of Wordpress or Mediawiki.</p>
<h1 id="rfc">RFC</h1>
<p>To that end, I want you to message me.  If any part of the documentation seems incomplete, or you run into anything stupid, <a href="https://twitter.com/tehshrike">message me on Twitter</a>.  If you think some part of the code is dumb, or you have questions about whether or not it could be bent to your own particular use case, <a href="mailto:me@JoshDuff.com">send me an email</a>.</p>
<p>If you want to contribute, I would be flattered and happy.  Submit an <a href="https://github.com/tehshrike/noddity/issues">issue</a> or pull request, and I will hug you if I ever meet you in person.  Unless you don't like that sort of thing, in which case I'll give you a cool-guy nod.</p>
<h1 id="to-infinity-and-beyond">To infinity and beyond</h1>
<p>I don't expect to make any great profits from Noddity, but I still want to work on improving it - easier theming, easier plugins, better parsing of wiki-links in the Markdown content.</p>
<p>If Noddity never grows, and simply stays as the cool backbone of 3-10 web sites for the rest of its existence, I won't be disappointed - I wrote it for my own use cases, and I'm satisfied so far.</p>
<p>But if Noddity grows, that would be sweet, and I'd love the excuse to put more polish into it.</p>
<p><a href="http://noddity.com">Check it out!</a></p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2014-11-22-noddity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2014-11-22-noddity.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 03:34:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why your webapp needs a state-based router]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Yeah, the title is slightly hyperbolic - state routers aren't appropriate for every webapp.  Your webapp probably needs one though!</p>
<h2 id="quick-intro">Quick intro</h2>
<p>Let's lay out a few definitions before diving in to avoid possible misunderstandings:</p>
<ul>
<li>webapp: a <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2015/01/22/native-web-apps">native web application</a> running in the browser that uses <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Guide/API/DOM/Manipulating_the_browser_history">pushState</a> to control navigation instead of sending the browser to a different html page.</li>
<li>router: any library that triggers your code when the url changes so you can update content in the dom.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="routing-in-a-webapp">Routing in a webapp</h2>
<p>Simple routers work something like this:</p>
<pre><code>route('/content/:name', function(params) {
    var name = params.name
    getContent(name, function(err, content) {
        $('.container').text(content) // insert your DOM manipulation framework here
    })
})
</code></pre>
<p>...which is all well and good.  My personal web site, the one you're probably reading this post on, uses such a simple router.</p>
<p>But when you start writing a more complex webapp, you will discover new desires within yourself.  You will begin to desire the ability to nest different parts of your webapp inside each other in some kind of hierarchy.</p>
<p><img style="width: 360px; height: 162px;" src="images/github-settings-submenu.png" alt="Github user settings screenshot"></p>
<p>Let's say you're making an account page that looks something like Github's here.</p>
<p>If your account page has a submenu that allows users to switch between "profile" and "account settings" forms, you have a few options:</p>
<ol>
<li>Neglect to put the current submenu's path in the url at all - if the user is at <code>/app/settings</code>, has the profile submenu open, and hits the refresh button, they pop back to whatever the default state is (maybe the profile page).  This is bad because they can't then hit the back button to go back to the last form, or send people links to a specific submenu on the settings page.</li>
<li>Represent the submenu in the url, instead of the page that contains it - you create routing rules for both <code>/app/settings-profile</code> and <code>/app/settings-account</code>, and both their templates just happen to contain that same menu on the left side.  This is bad because you have to re-render the menu every time, and you can't link to the settings page without setting up a settings route that is just a redirect, or linking directly to a default sub-page.</li>
<li>Make the submenu a parameter of the settings route - so inside a single route handler for <code>/app/settings/:submenu</code>, you put a big if block in your template that says "if the submenu parameter is 'profile' embed the profile page, else if it's 'account' embed that page..." etc etc.  This is awkward, and doesn't scale well past one level of nesting.</li>
<li>Use a solution that lets you nest your views, and handles interpreting the url to realize that <code>/app/settings/profile</code> should display the main logged-in app view, with the settings page inside of that, and the profile sub-page inside of that.  <strong>This is the good option!</strong></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="in-the-bad-ol-days">In the bad 'ol days</h2>
<p>I first used AngularJS <a href="http://www.edatasource.com/">at work</a> on a project that began in mid-2013.  Like every other Angular app at the time, we used the simple <a href="https://docs.angularjs.org/api/ngRoute/provider/$routeProvider">$routeProvider</a> exposed by the framework.</p>
<p>We had one route for the login screen, and another for each of the two different screens inside the app.  There was a lot of shared ui around the edges of the app, with the menu and search bar and everything, so both of those screen's routes used the same template, something like this:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;div id="main"&gt;
    &lt;div id="search-bar"&gt;
        &lt;input type="text" magical-autocomplete&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="menu"&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="" ng-click="navigateTo('page1')"&gt;Page 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="" ng-click="navigateTo('page2')"&gt;Page 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="content"&gt;
        &lt;div ng-include="template.urlOfActualTemplate"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Navigating to Page 1 or Page 2 would set <code>scope.template.urlOfActualTemplate = 'this-screen/screen-template.html'</code> and that would get displayed via the <code>ng-include</code>.</p>
<p>Pretty ugly.  Everything that we wanted serialized to the url was manually synchronized to a querystring parameter.  We never even considered going to the effort of representing further nested states by adding something like <code>&amp;childScreen=profile</code> to the querystring.</p>
<h2 id="and-then-i-fell-into-the-light">And then I fell into the light</h2>
<p>When the time came to begin our next AngularJS project, I turned to the barely-maintained-but-still-useful <a href="https://github.com/ngbp/ngbp">ngbp</a> Angular boilerplate.  One of the modules it included out of the box was <a href="https://github.com/angular-ui/ui-router">ui-router</a>.</p>
<p>ui-router is one of those solutions where once you've seen it in use, you can feel certain programming problems clearing up right in front of you.  ui-router allows you to:</p>
<ul>
<li>nest views or "states" inside of each other</li>
<li>associate url routes and querystring parameters with states so that changing the url changes any number of currently displayed states</li>
<li>indicate which states are associated with which parameters in the url</li>
</ul>
<p>This gives you the power to write each state as its own little module - you don't have to manually watch for changes to the querystring, because if any relevant parameter changes, your state goes away and a fresh new version of the state is instantiated.  Each state is its own little island and changes on navigation independently of any parent/child states.</p>
<p><img style="width: 467px; height: 187px;" src="images/analyst-menu-hierarchy.png" alt="Analyst Nextgen menu hierarchy"></p>
<p>This screenshot is from my employer's product.  Each of those three menus is a different nested state that allows you to drill down to a different child state.  And the url routing is a dream!</p>
<h2 id="but-angular">but... Angular</h2>
<p>I'm a child of the node/npm revolution, and as such I'm pretty framework-averse.  I prefer disconnected modules that solve problems that I can compose myself.</p>
<p>I'm especially averse to AngularJS 1.x, as it forces so many bad decisions down your throat (a module system with no difference between private and public APIs, all view-facing data on a $scope that uses dirty-checking to detect changes, and an inscrutable testing API).</p>
<p>ui-router is a fantastic library, solving a commonplace yet difficult problem, and solving it very well.  However, it's not worth using AngularJS just to be able to use ui-router.</p>
<p>I looked for similar libraries, but the only ones I found (<a href="https://github.com/rackt/react-router">react-router</a> and <a href="http://guides.emberjs.com/v1.10.0/routing/defining-your-routes/">Ember's router</a>) are similarly tied to their chosen rendering/templating tools.</p>
<h2 id="so-i-made-my-own">So I made my own</h2>
<p>I want to build business webapps without tying myself to a specific framework, allowing me to try new solutions at will.  I know that no matter what rendering or templating library I use at the time, my webapps need a state router.  Thus, <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/abstract-state-router">abstract-state-router</a>!</p>
<p>Built with help from <a href="https://github.com/ArtskydJ">ArtskydJ</a>, abstract-state-router is heavily inspired by ui-router, intended to be used with whatever templating library you like.  At the time of this writing, renderers have been set up for <a href="http://www.ractivejs.org/">Ractive.JS</a>, <a href="https://muut.com/riotjs/">Riot</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/Matt-Esch/virtual-dom">virtual-dom</a> - and it's not too difficult to <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/abstract-state-router/blob/master/renderer.md">implement new ones</a> with your favorite template/dom manipulation library.</p>
<p>The documentation is <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/abstract-state-router">on Github</a>.  I don't have good introductory wiki pages like ui-router's yet, though there is an <a href="http://tehshrike.github.io/state-router-example/">example todo app</a> using each of the current rendering/templating options.</p>
<h2 id="you-should-use-it">You should use it!</h2>
<p>If you're making a webapp that is more complex than a simple content site like this blog, you need a state-based router, and I'd like to help you use this one.</p>
<p>If you have a favorite template/dom manipulation library that you want to use, let me know and I'll help you write the renderer so that you can use it with abstract-state-router.</p>
<p>If you run into any difficulties, open an issue on Github or ping me on Twitter.</p>
<p>The module is out on npm for you to try - <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/abstract-state-router">check it out on Github</a>!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2015-06-why-you-need-a-state-router.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2015-06-why-you-need-a-state-router.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 00:05:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Side project post-partum: Communal Checklist]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>A wild side project appears!</p>
<p>My wife was looking for a site to set up a gift registry.  She tried several sites, but they weren't great - Amazon and Target have pretty good registries, but only if you lock your friends into buying from that one store.</p>
<p>There are more open-ended registries, but most of them require that your friends create accounts, and one of the most reasonable ones forces you to create multiple rows for each item if you wanted people to be able to indicate that they were buying say, only one of the two needed pajamas.</p>
<p>My finely-tuned programmer senses tingled.  A simple CRUD webapp, something like a custom to-do list - I should be able to whip up a servicable app in a few evenings!  I could call it the Communal Checklist.</p>
<p>Fast forward to about a month later.  After putting in 30-90 minutes coding every two or three days, I have finally deployed version 1.0.  Here's what I learned!</p>
<h2 id="my-tools-are-getting-better-but-i-need-to-put-them-first">My tools are getting better but I need to put them first</h2>
<p>My first bad decision was to not use the <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/abstract-state-router">abstract-state-router</a>.  I didn't think it was necessary - the Communal Checklist is nearly a literal single-page application, with one home screen and one editing/viewing screen.  A simple router like <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/hash-brown-router">hash-brown-router</a> should be plenty.</p>
<p>I forgot about the other niceities provided by the abstract-state-router - without it, I had to</p>
<ol>
<li>load asynchronous data after the template has been displayed, and handle both the "loading data" and "data done loading" states</li>
<li>deal with (or in my case, convince myself I could ignore) cleaning up event listeners on route change instead of getting a nice clean <code>destroy</code> event if the state parameters changed</li>
<li>actually care about where the template would be inserted, and manually create the Ractive object at that DOM location (just the <code>&lt;body&gt;</code> element in this case, but still annoying)</li>
</ol>
<p>Turns out the abstract-state-router isn't just for medium-to-large webapps, it's handy for small apps too.  I should have used it instead of imagining that a library with a slightly smaller API would make my app simpler.</p>
<h2 id="i-should-have-considered-the-project-as-an-excuse-to-keep-developing-my-tools">I should have considered the project as an excuse to keep developing my tools</h2>
<p>Communal Checklist was, in my mind, something I could have ready for my wife to use in a couple evenings.  No need to work in any tools I wasn't already familiar with, I planned to just make the app and move on.</p>
<p>Specifically, I opted to not use a <a href="https://gist.github.com/staltz/868e7e9bc2a7b8c1f754">reactive programming</a> library when hooking up my user interface.  I've been experimenting with the reactive programming library <a href="https://baconjs.github.io/">Bacon.js</a> lately and putting together some tools to make those libraries easier for me to use, but I haven't actually used a reactive programming library in an app yet.</p>
<p>It turns out, even for relatively simple apps, hooking together business logic behind a view (even a sexy view interface like <a href="http://www.ractivejs.org/">RactiveJS</a>) isn't that pretty.  If I handled user changes with a reactive streaming library, development may have felt slightly slower at first, but the code would have ended up simpler.</p>
<p>In addition to not slowing down development in reality, using Bacon.js to hook up a real app would have given me practical experience that would have been valuable as I use it to hook together my next, much more complicated apps.</p>
<h2 id="make-sure-to-clarify-specs">Make sure to clarify specs...</h2>
<p>I proudly showed my wife the beta slightly less than two weeks after I started.  She poked around a bit and then asked "how do I add categories?"</p>
<p>An entirely reasonable request.  I hadn't considered splitting lists up into sections.</p>
<p>Allowing items to be divvied up between different categories required small changes on the server-side to handle the changed data structure, but it took a bit more work on the client-side.</p>
<h3 id="which-made-the-code-slightly-more-complicated">Which made the code slightly more complicated</h3>
<p>In theory I could have just added another level of nested loops to the template and plowed forwards, adding to the long list of functions in my single list.js file, but I had already pushed past a level of code complexity that I was comfortable with.</p>
<p>This was the first real app I'd made with RactiveJS without using the abstract-state-router, and I'd never had to figure out how to nest templates properly in Ractive.</p>
<p>In AngularJS, I would have already created a second directive to represent a single list item, and adding category support would have just involved creating a new "category" directive to layer between the main template and the item template.</p>
<p>The Ractive documentation revealed <a href="http://docs.ractivejs.org/latest/components">components</a> to be the reasonable choice.  I broke out list items into their own template with their own associated code and created a new category template.</p>
<p>If I had been on the ball from the beginning I would have been using isolated scopes to make things simpler.</p>
<h2 id="ordered-arguments-are-evil-srsly">Ordered arguments are evil srsly</h2>
<p>I lost a couple hours tracking down bugs caused by emitting lists of 5+ arguments to the socket.io listeners on the server side.  I wasn't consistent on the argument order between all my functions, and I paid the price.</p>
<p>You'd think I would have learned by now!  Ordered arguments are evil.</p>
<p>I switched to emitting objects with named properties and everything became simple again.</p>
<h2 id="sweet-stylez">Sweet stylez</h2>
<p>I used a <a href="http://bootswatch.com/">Bootswatch</a> Bootstrap theme again.  Instant classy site design!  Biggest downside: it uses Google hosted fonts, making it impossible to work on the site without internet access to Google CDNs.</p>
<h3 id="responsive">Responsive</h3>
<p>Another buzzword achieved!  I decided to actually put the effort into making the site look good at small sizes.  I'd used Bootstrap's grid layout from the beginning - it turns out that making it properly responsive just involved giving all my rows a column width for every size.  w00t!</p>
<h2 id="storage-not-a-real-database">Storage: not a real database</h2>
<p>I am quite attracted to the <a href="http://lebron.technology/">LEBRON</a> stack.  I've used <a href="https://github.com/Level/levelup">LevelUP</a> a good bit in the past, for Noddity and other projects - it's an excellent interface to a key-value store.  And from what I've heard, LevelDB is quite a good flat-file key-value store - it's the SQLite of key-value stores, and SQLite is awesome!</p>
<p>So I took the plunge - I wrote and deployed a webapp using a <a href="http://howfuckedismydatabase.com/nosql/">nosql</a> database.</p>
<p>It's a pretty defensible choice - I don't expect traffic to go out of control, and using LevelUP as my interface means I can relatively easily switch to other backends besides LevelDB.  The simple key-value store makes local testing easy, and deployments are as simple as <code>npm install</code>.</p>
<p>Yet, if I were starting today, this is another choice I would make differently.</p>
<p>Using a key-value store actually made my server-side code more complex than it needed to be.</p>
<p>In order to read and update a list category or a category's item with a single read, I have to store the whole tree at the same key.</p>
<p>To update a list item, I have to look up the list by its id (my one lookup), iterate over the categories to find the one with the correct id, and then iterate over the category's items to find the id that is being updated.  I then copy the changed values over to the original document, and save the whole thing back in at the list's key.</p>
<p>I realize that more advanced document stores have better tools for working with child documents, but most of the attraction of the key-value store for me is being able to use LevelUP as an interface.</p>
<p>Maybe I should have stored lists, categories, and items at their own keys and suffered the extra lookups in exchange for simpler code.  Or maybe I should have just used a database that supported SQL.</p>
<p>Relational databases are actually pretty sweet.</p>
<h3 id="will-it-scale">Will it scale?</h3>
<p>I have no idea!  I figure it will at least make it past the baby shower.</p>
<p>Honestly though, the benchmarks that LevelDB advertises are far beyond what I expect this app to ever have put against it, even in the unlikely event that the Communal Checklist turns into a bustling hub of gift registries.</p>
<h2 id="passive-income">Passive income!</h2>
<p>Communal Checklist represents my first attempt at generating passive income.  Every time someone adds a link to an Amazon item, my affiliate code is automatically attached.</p>
<p>If my site does ever start getting regular traffic, this may lead to some small regular income, as Amazon is a monster of internet shopping (though I understand that when it comes to first-party gift registries, Target still provides a better experience for now).</p>
<h2 id="yet-to-do">Yet to do</h2>
<p>The most obvious missing feature that I know of is the inability to reorder items.  If many people start using the site, I'll give <a href="https://github.com/bevacqua/dragula">dragula</a> another try (I couldn't figure out how to get the dragging styles to work in my first quick try).</p>
<p>Other assorted TLC would include testing the app more thoroughly on phones and touchscreens, and figuring out how to make the checkboxes larger and friendlier.</p>
<p>In the short term, I plan to slim down the CSS and inline the webfonts to increase the loading speed.  I also recently added gzipping of static content on <code>npm run build</code>.</p>
<p>These further improvements probably won't happen unless the site sees regular traffic going forward.  Speaking of which, I suppose I need to set up some kind of analytics, too.  Does anyone know of a reasonable analytics site that Google Analytics?</p>
<h2 id="in-conclusion">In conclusion</h2>
<p>Like everything else I make, the code to Communal Checklist is <a href="https://github.com/TehShrike/communal-checklist">public on Github</a> and is licensed <a href="http://wtfpl2.com/">WTFPL</a>.</p>
<p>If you want a lightweight gift-registry/checklist collaboration app that doesn't require you to sign in, go to <a href="http://communalchecklist.com/">communalchecklist.com</a>!</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2015-09-communal-checklist.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2015-09-communal-checklist.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 18:04:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Writing SQL for applications]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>For about the last decade I've been writing business software backed by relational databases.  Working with my teammates, I have acquired conventions for writing schema and production queries that make interacting with the database simpler and easier.</p>
<p>These conventions primarily optimize for <strong>reading or writing queries in production code</strong>.</p>
<p>I believe it is fair to say that for most business applications, the schema + data <em>is</em> the application, with the rest of the code there to make the application easy to work with.</p>
<p>As Patrick McKenzie likes to remind us, most of our industry is built on building specialized spreadsheets.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Every spreadsheet shared in a business is an angel announcing another SaaS app still needs to be built.</p>
<p> <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/655674551615942657">@patio11</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The less friction involved in interacting with the underlying data, the greater our ability to develop our application.</p>
<h1 id="schema-design-conventions">Schema design conventions</h1>
<p>Most of the conventions in schema design enable two things:</p>
<p>First, the ability to write queries without having to look up a bunch of table schemas to remind yourself what the column names are, or spelling idiosyncrasies.</p>
<p>Second, looking at a single table and quickly understanding all of its relationships.</p>
<h2 id="the-primary-key-column-should-be-either-id-or-the-table-name-suffixed-with-_id">The primary key column should be either <code>id</code>, or the table name suffixed with <code>_id</code></h2>
<p>It's a matter of preference whether you use <code>customer_id</code> versus <code>id</code> as the primary key column of the <code>customer</code> table, you could make arguments either direction - just apply the convention consistently.</p>
<p>The actual suffix/name doesn't matter, but <code>_id</code> seems to be the most common convention.</p>
<p>The main point is that whatever suffix you pick should be consistent across the entire schema.  This lets you join to another table without having to remember anything but the table name.</p>
<h2 id="foreign-keys-should-always-contain-the-name-of-the-table-they-link-to">Foreign keys should always contain the name of the table they link to</h2>
<p>If rows in your <code>invoice</code> table link to rows in your <code>customer</code> table, the invoice table should be named <code>customer_id</code>, not <code>buyer_id</code> or <code>purchaser_id</code>.</p>
<p>This convention lets you know what the foreign keys of a table are referencing just by looking at the output from <code>DESCRIBE tablename</code>, which makes writing queries easier.  It also makes queries in code easier to follow.</p>
<p>Sometimes the name of the column by itself isn't enough - for example, besides the purchasing customer, your invoice might have a <code>referrer_customer_id</code>.  As long as the column ends with the <code>[tablename]_id</code> for the table you're linking to, everything is good and easy to read.  Naming that column <code>referrer_id</code> makes your schema much more difficult to read and requires you to memorize a bunch of special-case names.</p>
<h2 id="all-tables-have-a-single-column-auto-increment-primary-key">All tables have a single-column auto-increment primary key</h2>
<p>This is something I waffled on a lot in my early years.  After all, isn't the primary key just an arbitrarily chosen candidate key?  Why not use a "natural" key, if one exists?</p>
<p>If you're using MySQL + InnoDB, there are real performance benefits to using an auto-increment primary key, but even if that were not the case I have become convinced that natural keys should not be used as the primary key.</p>
<p>No matter how sure you are that a natural candidate key will never change, and that all the values in the key are immutable after being inserted, it is very likely that at some point, business concerns will require that some of the values be changed, breaking all foreign key references and caches throughout your system.</p>
<p>That fear alone is pretty motivating.  But beyond that I have found that when foreign keys use identifiers that don't have any business concern outside of the database, queries are easier to write and mutating state in tables becomes less scary.</p>
<h2 id="no-abbreviations-in-table-or-column-names">No abbreviations in table or column names</h2>
<p>Abbreviations and otherwise shortened labels make your schema difficult to read, and incomprehensible to people who don't spend every minute in the project.  Saving those occasional keystrokes is not worth it.</p>
<p>Making an exception for industry-standard abbreviations is fine - in the car parts inventory industry, <code>vin</code> is a reasonable column name, and <code>esp</code> is an acceptable table name in the email marketing industry.</p>
<p>Using abbreviations that you come up with yourself, or drpping vwls to sv chars is counterproductive.</p>
<h2 id="no-plural-table-names">No plural table names</h2>
<p>This is one of the simplest conventions, but the one that causes the most annoyance when ignored.</p>
<p>If your schema has a mix of pluralized and non-pluralized table names, you will forever be referring to your list of table names to remember if you should be typing <code>customer</code> or <code>customers</code>.</p>
<p>Half the time I see someone with a plural table name, they leave the <code>s</code> off of some or all of the key references - does the invoice table contain a <code>customer_id</code> column, or a <code>customers_id</code> column?  I dunno, better go look.</p>
<p>Just remember that the table name should be representative of what a single row contains.  A row in the <code>invoice</code> table contains an <code>invoice</code>, not <code>invoices</code>.</p>
<p>This will allow you to write queries with many joins without having to look up a bunch of column/table names.</p>
<h1 id="query-conventions">Query conventions</h1>
<p>These conventions all have the goal of making queries in production code easier to read and maintain.</p>
<h2 id="no-select">No <code>SELECT *</code></h2>
<p>Perhaps the most <a href="http://www.parseerror.com/blog/select-*-is-evil">commonly-known SQL antipattern</a>.</p>
<p>Queries should specify exactly the columns that you require.  There are performance implications, but beyond that, your queries should be explicit about what they are doing, for the reader's benefit.</p>
<p><em>NOTE: as of ~2020 I no longer subscribe to this convention  there are legitimate cases where <code>SELECT *</code> is valid and useful, e.g. "I want to get the entire customer object from the database" where you really want the whole thing no matter how many columns it is.</em></p>
<h2 id="no-aliases">No aliases</h2>
<p>I see lots of developers aliasing table names in production queries.</p>
<pre><code>SELECT i.total
FROM invoice AS i
WHERE i.customer_id = ?
</code></pre>
<p>This reduces the number of characters you type at the expense of taking more work to read the query when someone comes across it in the code later.  Don't make that tradeoff!</p>
<p>Developers shouldn't have to pull in a bunch of specialized naming context to be able to understand a query.  You want to be able to read over any part of the query and understand what columns are being used without having to read over the from and join clauses to memorize any aliases.</p>
<p>There's an obvious exception for when you need to reference the same table twice in different from/join clauses.  When writing production queries, you should still try to make the alias meaningful!</p>
<pre><code>FROM invoice
JOIN invoice AS other_invoices_from_same_customer ON other_invoices_from_same_customer.customer_id = invoice.customer_id
    AND other_invoices_from_same_customer.invoice_id != invoice.invoice_id
</code></pre>
<h2 id="always-use-table-identifiers-in-multi-table-queries">Always use table identifiers in multi-table queries</h2>
<p>Similarly, if you consistently use table names in column identifiers, you make it easier to read over your query in smaller chunks.  <code>SELECT customer_id</code> is less meaningful than <code>SELECT invoice.customer_id</code>.</p>
<p>This convention does make it easier to add joins to existing queries.  However, in my mind the primary advantage is the improved readability.</p>
<h2 id="uppercase-everything-except-identifiers">Uppercase everything except identifiers</h2>
<p>Sadly, I haven't yet worked with a code editor that applied SQL syntax highlighting inside of static strings.</p>
<p>Uppercasing the non-identifier parts of the SQL (e.g. <code>FROM invoice</code> instead of <code>from invoice</code>) makes queries embedded in code easier to read.</p>
<h2 id="newlines-before-each-query-clause">Newlines before each query clause</h2>
<p>A query is composed of an ordered list of components called "clauses".  Queries are easier to read when the clauses are separated by newlines.</p>
<pre><code>SELECT SUM(invoice.total)
FROM customer
JOIN invoice ON invoice.invoice_id = customer.customer_id
    AND invoice.finalized = TRUE
WHERE customer.customer_id = ?
</code></pre>
<p>As opposed to</p>
<pre><code>SELECT SUM(invoice.total) FROM customer JOIN invoice ON invoice.invoice_id = customer.customer_id AND invoice.finalized = TRUE
WHERE customer.customer_id = ?
</code></pre>
<p>You and your team can come up with your own conventions around the rest of the whitespace, but I think newlines before each clause are a must for readability.</p>
<h1 id="personal-context">Personal context</h1>
<p>I've worked on evolving schemas with hundreds of tables.  Following these conventions has made life demonstrably better.  Frustration is decreased, less time is wasted.</p>
<p>I have spent countless nights helping people with schema and query issues in <a href="http://hashmysql.org/">#mysql</a> on Freenode, and the <a href="http://chat.stackoverflow.com/rooms/592/mysql-and-relational-databases">MySQL room on StackOverflow</a>.  Most developers do not appear to follow strong conventions like these.</p>
<p>At ISoft, in the early days of <a href="http://wikido.isoftdata.com/index.php/ITrack/Enterprise">ITrack Enterprise</a>, we were able to take a week and refactor the hodge-podge of tables (probably 80 at the time), bringing them in line with the conventions we had set up at the time, and updating the code to match.</p>
<p>This paid off enormously over the years as the application was deployed to many customers and the schema grew to ~200 tables.  Not many applications get that chance, though - you have to evolve your schema while continuing to deliver features and fixes.</p>
<p>It's not hopeless - you can achieve an easy-to-work-with schema - as long as your team is on board, you leave things better than you found them when working in an area of the schema.</p>
<p>This is something I'm still working on!  I got super-excited to learn more after listening to Neal Ford's <em>Continuous Delivery: Infrastructure and Data</em> talk at Uberconf, and am following his recommendation to read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321774515/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0321774515&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=josduf-20&amp;linkId=5983034458d49f14545009fbc8d5b31f">Refactoring Databases: Evolutionary Database Design</a>.</p>
<h1 id="in-conclusion">In conclusion</h1>
<p>Your application is defined by its schema and the queries you use to interact with it.  Embrace it!  Keep it simple!  It will pay off.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2016-07-writing-sql.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2016-07-writing-sql.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 01:11:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to remote pair-code usefully]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I like pair-coding and think it can be great.  Done well, it multiplies the abilities/usefulness of two developers, rather than just adding them together.</p>
<p>The easiest way to pair in a remote setting is one person driving the keyboard and sharing their screen, and one person observing and communicating verbally or by sending code snippets via direct message.</p>
<p>The observer can provide a lot of value by</p>
<ul>
<li>reading the driver's code as it is being written and mentally validating that it solves the problem at hand (kind of like a linter, but for business logic)</li>
<li>looking up documentation or searching Stack Overflow so that driver doesn't have to mode-switch away from the code they're staring at</li>
<li>validating or checking assumptions that the driver is making</li>
<li>asking questions about current/next steps</li>
</ul>
<p>The better the driver is at "programming out loud" and narrating their thought process, the easier it is for the observer to provide value.</p>
<p>If the observer is paying attention and knows what you're trying to do, the driver can often bang out code pretty efficiently, trusting the observer to catch issues on the fly that would have burned time in tracking them down later.</p>
<h2 id="distracted-coding-kills">Distracted coding kills</h2>
<p>If the driver or the observer (especially the observer) ever get distracted and aren't highly engaged in what you're working on, it can suck all the energy out of the session and make it difficult to spin back up again.</p>
<p>If something happens that you really need to pay attention to, you should immediately say "I need to step away for a bit" and disconnect from the call until you're able to be engaged again.</p>
<p>It's really great to be able to lean on someone else's brain while problem-solving.  If they're not engaged, leaning on their brain will lead to falling over, and train you not to count on them.</p>
<h2 id="communicating-verbally-while-coding-can-be-frustrating">Communicating verbally while coding can be frustrating</h2>
<p>Verbalizing what you are trying to do to another human while you're in coding-mode can be really difficult if you're not used to it.</p>
<p>Don't give up on it  it gets easier as you exercise it, and I believe the skill transfers over to lots of other communicating-with-prose-about-code contexts.</p>
<p>One of the reasons I dislike screen-sharing tools like Screenhero that let you click/type on the other person's screen is because it lets you give in to the "it's hard to explain, just let me do it".</p>
<p>Having to explain it with words is where a lot of the value comes from, and I believe it levels up your ability to communicate as teammates.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2021-08-24-pair-coding.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2021-08-24-pair-coding.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 18:28:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Eschatology of software]]></title><description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p><strong>Eschatology:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>System of doctrines concerning final matters, such as death.</li>
<li>The study of the end times  the end of the world, notably in Christian and Islamic theology, the second coming of Christ, the Apocalypse or the Last Judgment.</li>
</ol>
<p><em> <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/eschatology">Wiktionary</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have worked with people who said "this code is bad.  I know that perfect software is possible.  But the employer will not authorize the months it would take to turn this particular code into perfect software, and so it can not be good.  To ask me to iteratively improve upon this code in my pull request is to ask for something unreasonable."</p>
<p>I have also worked with people who came from a place of authority  they had worked on what they knew to be Good Software.  They said "this model for writing code is correct.  It will produce good software."  In a discussion about how the software could be vastly better in the future if the code was written differently, they said "that is not the method that is known to produce Good Software.  We should continue using this method."</p>
<p>The former could talk about better code, but could not write it.  The latter could write decent code, but couldn't write better code.</p>
<h2 id="why-not-both-gif">Why Not Both.gif</h2>
<p>The biblical eschatology of humans says that we are fallen, sinful, shitty humans.  Yet the Bible expects us to obsess about God's perfect law<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn1" id="fnref1">[1]</a></sup>, and the perfection of Jesus, our human model.  We are not expected to achieve that perfection in our lifetimes, but we are expected to iterate on the fallen state we find ourselves in.</p>
<p>My eschatology of software is that I have been given a fallen, sinful, shitty codebase.  I should obsess over the ideal perfect software that I could theoretically ship.  And I should be constantly iterating the codebase towards that perfection, while understanding that it will never achieve perfection in its lifetime or mine.</p>
<hr class="footnotes-sep">
<section class="footnotes">
<ol class="footnotes-list">
<li class="footnote-item" id="fn1"><p><a href="https://canonreader.com/text/psalms?highlight=119_97-119_97#chapter-119-verse-97">Psalm 119:97</a> <a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref1"></a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2022-02-07-eschatology-of-software.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2022-02-07-eschatology-of-software.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 16:34:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The first letter I wrote to Anna]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I sent this letter 10 years ago today.</p>
<p>We were engaged 5 months later.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This is a weird letter to write, I've been trying to start it for several days now!  I've mulled over lots of monologues I could send, but then I begin to worry that I'm getting too deep or too off-topic or too inappropriate and throw it out to begin another one.  I think I'll try for shorter and simple for now - please excuse my clumsiness.</p>
<p>To be honest, I didn't expect our fathers to complete their initial correspondance so quickly.  I think I had this fantasy that a new job opportunity would roll around within a month or so, and I'd be all moved to Omaha and getting ready to start the serious business of finding a wife at around the same time our parents were wrapping up their opening dialogs with each other, or something like that.</p>
<p>Among other things, I'm fairly certain that God is working on disabusing me of my own life-scheduling abilities.  I'm trying to learn the lesson gracefully.</p>
<p>Your father suggested that we begin by communicating to establish a friendship, which seems quite reasonable.  I would appreciate being able to write back and forth with you on any topic, but I do want to make my intentions clear.</p>
<p>I have observed a tendency among many people in our generation to pursue friendship with someone of the opposite sex, with a vague goal in mind that they would pursue a romantic relationship after they've been friends for a while, if they feel like it.</p>
<p>I'm not against communicating for the purpose of adding to my repetoire of friends, but that is not my goal here.  I would like to pursue friendship with the goal of searching out whether or not it would be wise to consider marriage to each other.</p>
<p>This doesn't mean you have to throw all your chips into the pot now, of course.  If it turns out at some point that marriage wouldn't be a good idea, that's fine!  I just don't want any ambiguity about my purposes.</p>
<p>Does that seem reasonable?  Does it seem too business-like?  My sisters would probably call this letter too matter-of-fact and devoid of emotion, but this isn't something that I want to risk messing up because I went about communicating sloppily!  (Not that emotional communication is necessarily sloppy, of course...  aaand I think I'll end this paragraph now.)</p>
<p>What would you feel comfortable talking about (if anything)?  Have you thought much of marriage before now?  I'm afraid to ask too many questions in the first letter without giving you a chance to weigh in on the tone of the communications, so I'll hold off on any more in this letter, but I would love to hear about the projects you enjoy working on.</p>
<p>One last thing I'm curious about: I saw you got an awesome banjo, and am curious if you've decided on clawhammer vs Scruggs style for picking yet?  I've been getting pretty big into bluegrass this last year, and I can't get enough of Noam Pikelny's banjo playing!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In retrospect I'm glad I was clear about making it about "should we get married or not" from day one.  It made everything simpler.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2022-09-10-my-first-letter-to-anna.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2022-09-10-my-first-letter-to-anna.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 15:04:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[My appendix experience]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I don't often feel the need to journal my experiences for posterity, but these last few days have been quite the outlier among my human experiences.</p>
<p>Earlier this week I was helping my in-laws pack up their home in Texas to move closer to their grandchildren.  Around noon on Tuesday the 27th, for my first food of the day, I ate a cookie bar that had been sitting on the counter (mostly covered) for the past two days.  Pretty shortly afterward, I felt some pain in my gut that I diagnosed as gas.  "Ah," I thought, "that's what I get for breaking my fast with something so carby."</p>
<p>The gas pain got more annoying throughout the day, and didn't seem to change when I ate a real meal a couple hours later.  I slept about three hours that night, but then woke up and spent most of the rest of the night changing positions and trying get myself to fart it out, to no success.</p>
<p>Wednesday we were driving the ~10 hour trip to Iowa, and I was supposed to drive most of the way in one of the cars.  At some point in the first few hours I got some pepto bismol at a gas station and took a couple doses.  I thought maybe it calmed my guts down slightly, but it didn't seem to do much.  The pain kept increasing.</p>
<p>About halfway through the drive I started to doubt that I was dealing with gas, and wondered if I had somehow developed some kind of severe constipation, even though I had managed a small bowel movement the night before.  Maybe there was some hardcore blockage behind that bit?  I started to really regret the pepto bismol, which would only make the constipation worse.  I didn't eat anything the whole day, the idea of food was not attractive at all.</p>
<p>I handed off driving for most of the trip, only driving for 3 or 4 hours total.  The plan was to drive to the Iowa house and empty the vehicle before driving the hour or so back to my house near Omaha, but a couple hours before arrival, the pain was starting to get pretty bad, so I requested to be dropped off at my home first.</p>
<p>My plan was still to try to deal with constipation: I knew we had magnesium citrate, which would turn any hard poops in my intestines into mush.  As soon as we got to my house I rushed to the master bathroom, chugged the full dose of magnesium citrate, and tried to empty myself, but with no luck.  If anything, my guts felt a little worse.</p>
<p>After 30-60 minutes, the pain was starting to get pretty debilitating.  My guts were throbbing.  There weren't any positions I could take that would relieve it, no stretching my legs apart or laying on my side would help at all.  My vision started to warp, it was the first time I've experienced "not seeing straight" because of pain.</p>
<p>Presumably due to proximity, the pain affected my groin, giving the aching sensation of having been kicked in the balls, but without fading away over time.</p>
<p>The only other pain I've felt to compare this to would be some of the awful earaches I had as a young teen, which were awful and lasted for hours.  These pains probably ranged in the 8-9 range on the pain scale.  Experiencing that level of pain in my guts didn't seem like much of an improvement over feeling it in my head.</p>
<p>Later I tried to think if I've ever actually hit a 10 on the pain scale, debilitated to the point where I couldn't even form words.  Maybe that time a piano bench full of books landed on my big toe and burst all the blood vessels?  But that 10 probably only lasted five to fifteen seconds before dropping down to an 8 or 9.</p>
<p>I messaged my mother "Could you diagnose appendicitis" and then spent about 30 seconds looking up <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appendicitis#Diagnosis">Appendicitis#Diagnosis</a> on Wikipedia.</p>
<p>Out of other options, unable to drive, and with my wife not able to drop the kids and drive me to the ER, I told my wife that I was calling 911 and she should let the paramedics into our room when they arrived.  I called 911 at 19:39 (7:39 PM).  I put on some clean clothes and laid on our bed on my back with my knees bent until they arrived.</p>
<p>They took vitals and got my story  "thought it was gas, then constipation, now it's really bad", and then got me into a cart and into the ambulance.  They asked me what hospital I wanted and I said <a href="https://bestcare.org/locations/methodist-hospital">Methodist</a>, having had a good experience there when dealing with hypertension in the last year.  And really, who wants to juggle medical records and doctor interactions and paperwork across multiple health systems.</p>
<p>Those ambulances don't have fantastic shocks.  It wasn't the driver's fault, but I could really feel all the bumps in my guts.  I was just trying to ride the pain and give any diagnostically useful answers that I could when people asked me questions.  I think I had to repeat a couple answers to the paramedics because they had trouble understanding my clipped speech in the vehicle.</p>
<p>The paramedic in charge must have been new to the job.  She seemed nervous and didn't want to make the call to the hospital on the way back, but another older paramedic made her do it.  Same vibes I remember from having to call a customer during my early weeks of software support at ISoft and explain them something that I didn't really understand myself.</p>
<p>They got me into an ER room and a nurse saw me quickly.  I gave them the story "thought gas, thought constipation, hurts real bad, check for appendicitis?" in the same "ride the pain, say diagnostically useful things when asked" mode.</p>
<p>They reasonably wanted blood and urine samples, but my deep bouncy veins caused the same problem they always do, and even the expert nurses weren't able to get a needle into them, so they called the IV ultrasound cart, which takes a little bit to show up.</p>
<p>They gave me a cup to pee in.  Sliding off of the bed to get to where I could pee was a bit rough.  I peed into the cup and managed to stop before it overflowed, and got the cap on.  At this point I could feel my stomach churning and got my mask off in time to start puking up the magnesium citrate syrup and water onto the floor.  I tried to holler for a bucket or something between pukes but couldn't be very loud.  At least my food-free puke was relatively easy to clean up.  The nurse threw some towels on it when she came in, and someone with a mopping device cleaned it up a little while later.</p>
<p>My parents showed up at some point around here.  I wasn't able to pay much attention to them, but it's always nice to have extra for "respectable middle-class, definitely not a drug-seeker" reinforcement around.  Not to mention the chance that they might catch or remember something that I would miss under the circumstances.</p>
<p>When the ultrasound showed up and they got an IV into my arm, they took the blood sample.  Some time not long afterward they offered me IV Tylenol, which sounded great.  I was ready for any pain medication and if there was something that would work without me taking an opiate, that was fine with me.</p>
<p>I mentioned to the nurse that I had never had opiates before and was happy to start with the IV Tylenol.  It started to work pretty quickly, I think it might have been 10-20 minutes before my pain started to drop from the 7-9 range down to 4-5.  I became able to hold a conversation with my parents and could think about things besides just hanging on.</p>
<p>I felt good enough to get up and walk to the bathroom and pee, though it was more work than I expected.  Even with the painkiller, urinating hurt more than I expected, mirroring the weird gut/groin connection from earlier.</p>
<p>The blood report came back with elevated white blood cell count, which I knew from my 30 seconds of Wikipedia research was an indicator of appendicitis.  The doctor spoke in a calm, steady voice and would inject absurd humorous statements into his sentences.  I suspect that tone helps keep an even keel in an ER setting.</p>
<p>They scheduled a CT scan to take a look at my appendix.  I think it took maybe 30-40 minutes before they took me up to get scanned?  The ER doctor came in a little while later and said "well, I'm afraid we're going to have to take you out back and shoot you."  He had eyeballed the CT results and saw a pretty clear case of acute appendicitis.  He couldn't schedule the surgery until after a radiologist checked it over and confirmed though.</p>
<p>After the appendicitis diagnosis, they offered me opioids: Dilaudid (a brand name of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydromorphone">Hydromorphone</a>, a morphine derivative), and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxycodone">Oxycodone</a>.  I was still feeling fine from the IV Tylenol so I said I'd stick with that for now.  The nurse asked me if I would be willing to take opioids later if the pain came back, and I said yes, definitely.</p>
<p>It had been about 3 hours from getting to the ER to getting the diagnosis.  After a little while someone in radiology gave the official "looks like pretty normal guts, except for the obvious nasty appendicitis" diagnosis, and they could schedule surgery.  They put me on the plate of a surgeon who was on call, but not in the hospital that night.  They weren't sure when the surgery was scheduled  the doctor could come in that night if it was urgent enough, or I might get scheduled for the next day.</p>
<p>They took me from the ER to my room in the surgery department some time around midnight.  Somewhere between 2:00 and 3:00, I woke up in pretty bad pain.  The IV Tylenol had worn off and my pain was back up to 6 or 7 and climbing.  I spent a few seconds debating trying to ride pain a while longer but that didn't last too long.  I hit the call button and told the nurse about the pain and then spent a while (maybe ten or fifteen minutes?  Hard to say) moaning while she got the drugs ready and did whatever software interactions were necessary to make the good drugs pop out.</p>
<p>She gave me Dilaudid via IV.  It didn't have the immediate pain-reducing effect I was hoping for, but the pain did slowly drop over the next 20 minutes or so.  After about 30 minutes I did notice some lightheadedness, but it didn't seem like a high particularly worth chasing, and I was way too tired to try to take notes on the minutia of the effects.  I suppose most people get hooked on those types of opioids not so much from the high, as much as how they feel awful when they try to stop taking it.</p>
<p>But it only lasted a few hours, and some time after 5:00 I woke up in pain again.  This time the nurse gave me an oxycodone pill.  Even though it wasn't via IV, it still seemed like it had fully kicked in within 20 or 30 minutes.  Unlike the Dilaudid, the effects lasted a long time  I didn't feel any increase of pain for at least 8 hours after that.  I'm sure effectiveness varies from person to person, but as far as I'm concerned, oxycodone is pretty great stuff.</p>
<p>My surgery was scheduled for 15:00 that day (Thursday), and the only other painkiller I asked for was some tylenol about 30 minutes before pre-op.  The single doses of Dilaudid and oxycodone were the only opioids I needed/got during my stay.</p>
<p>Once the morning came and I learned that my surgery was scheduled for the afternoon, there wasn't a lot for me to do, though honestly I was so worn out and catching up from the sleep deficit of the night before that I was fine just laying there and napping.  I got up to pee once or twice, but discovered that moving around was only asking for pain that would take a while to fade away, so I quickly got accustomed to staying pretty flat on my back.</p>
<p>Even though the oxycodone worked well, I could still feel a constant throbbing around my lower abdomen.  It wasn't debilitating, but it was a constant reminder that there was something inside of me that was going to kill me if something didn't kill it first.</p>
<p>My diet orders were "NPO", which apparently is an acronym for some latin meaning "nothing by mouth", but I interpreted as "nothing pre-op".  Not an issue for me, food had zero appeal.</p>
<p>My mom was able to watch the kids so my wife could come visit me for a couple hours before pre-op.  I didn't feel up to having the kids energy around at that point, but it was great to have my wife there.  I had been away helping her folks move since 6 days earlier, and we hadn't been able to properly kiss when I rushed in the door a couple hours before calling 911.</p>
<p>They rolled me down to pre-op about an hour before surgery was scheduled.  The anesthetist came in and prescribed a cocktail of drugs to reduce the odds of me feeling awful or puking after waking up.  I think two of them were to reduce the power of my stomach acid.  They must have worked, I didn't feel any nausea afterward.</p>
<p>I suppose sitting in pre-op waiting to get wheeled into surgery would have been a natural time to feel anxiety about the surgery, but I had fully internalized "either this thing comes out, or I die an awful death", so it wasn't like there was any chance I was making a wrong decision, and I didn't feel any fear or nervousness.  After 30 minutes or so they wheeled me in.</p>
<p>The surgery room looked surprisingly warehousey.  I think the floor was concrete.  Bright light overhead, of course.  The nurse who wheeled me in seemed like an old hand and gave me a quick run-down of what would happen.  She wheeled my cot next to the surgery table, got them to the same level, and had me scootch my way over onto the table and get myself centered.</p>
<p>"Ooh, you were trained to be modest," said the nurse, when she discovered that the lower half of my open-backed hospital gown was tied shut, as she reached underneath me and untied it.</p>
<p>Before putting the mask on they told me it would give me oxygen, which seemed somewhat disingenuous since I was pretty sure the anesthetic was the most relevant stuff.  I think I was out within one or two seconds of the mask going on.</p>
<p>I woke up back in my room some time around the neighborhood of 17:00 with people getting my bed settled and taking my vitals and such.  I was able to ask them a few questions and felt slightly proud for being reasonably cogent, having seen videos of people acting super-high while coming out of anesthesia.</p>
<p>The answer to "is there any chance of me going home today" was "no", which was slightly disappointing since the surgeon had made it sound like going home the day of the surgery was at least theoretically possible.  I didn't feel like complaining though.  The awful throbbing in my front was gone, but I was really tired.  They gave me a cup of chicken broth and told me to sleep off the anesthesia.  I said my pain level was 0.</p>
<p>I woke up around 21:30 with a much clearer head, still feeling great.  I messaged some friends to give updates, and asked for another cup of broth.  After a couple hours of catching up on communication I turned on <a href="https://www.omnibusproject.com/">Omnibus</a> and went back to sleep.</p>
<p>The surgeon saw me briefly in the morning.  Everything seemed fine, my abdomen felt pretty sore if I tried to flex it and I couldn't do anything close to a sit-up, but it didn't really hurt and I reported my pain as 0.  It took a while for the "is he officially discharged yet?" dance to conclude, but eventually I was out the door and catching a ride home.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laparoscopy">Laparoscopic surgery</a> is pretty cool!  I only have three small holes in me.  Twenty years ago a good friend of mine had his appendix removed, and he got the traditional long straight scar.  I'm hoping the smaller footprint gives me a quick recovery, though I'm still moving fairly slow a day after getting home now, and getting up from laying prone is still a small ordeal.</p>
<p>My experience with Methodist Hospital was great.  Like my last visit, all the nurses and doctors seemed on the ball and actually cared about doing well for the patients.  They were all cogs in a giant bureaucratic machine, but it didn't seem like they felt it prevented them from doing a good job.  Everyone seemed friendly and competent.</p>
<p>I praise the Lord for the good health care I have access to.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2022-10-01-appendix-experience.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2022-10-01-appendix-experience.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 17:44:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Contra Jane Jacobs on a biblical history of cities]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>In <em>The Economy Of Cities</em>, Jane Jacobs argues that cities have always been the locus of human economy.</p>
<p>The default story of pre-history given by a lot of books is that humans did agricultural work on distributed farms, and then built up cities when they got wealthier.</p>
<p>She refutes this idea, saying that cities have always been the starting place for human culture and production, and makes some pretty convincing arguments.</p>
<p>She attributes the incorrect idea of the historic agrarian -&gt; city transition at least in part to Adam Smith, and blames his assumptions on the Bible:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At the time Smith was writing, educated men in Europe still believed that both the world and men had been created almost simultaneously, about 5,000 B.C., and that man was born into a garden. So Smith never asked how agriculture arose. Agriculture and animal husbandry were givens; they were the original ways in which men earned their bread by the sweat of their brows.</p>
<p>For Smith, in the 1770s, the question had to be, How did commerce and industry arise upon agriculture?no matter what the evidence might suggest to the contrary. And so Smith had to propose a very special chain of economic causes and effects unlike any observable since, but presumably in operation at the beginning of the world. In short, he was not able to indulge his imagination while sticking to known processes; he had to invent chains of imaginary causes and effects.*</p>
<p>Adam Smith thus converted biblical history into economic doctrine.</p>
<p> <em>The Economy of Cities, towards the end of chapter 1</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't know if Smith really was deriving his assumptions from the Bible, but I disagree with Jacobs that those suppositions naturally derive from the Bible.  I think the Bible actually supports her argument!</p>
<h2 id="what-was-cain-s-punishment">What was Cain's punishment</h2>
<p>In the first recorded murder, Cain kills his brother.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Yahweh said, What have you done? The voice of your brothers blood cries to me from the ground.</p>
<p>Now you are cursed because of the ground, which has opened its mouth to receive your brothers blood from your hand.</p>
<p>From now on, when you till the ground, it wont yield its strength to you. You will be a fugitive and a wanderer in the earth.</p>
<p>Cain said to Yahweh, My punishment is greater than I can bear.</p>
<p> <em>Genesis 4:10-13a</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>What did it mean to be a fugitive?  I would argue that one reason this would hit Cain so hard is because humanity was probably all living in the same place, whereever Adam and Eve had settled after being thrown out of the garden.</p>
<p>So Cain gets sent away from civilization, and what's the first thing he does?  He builds a city.  (Genesis 4:16)</p>
<h2 id="where-did-noah-s-kids-live">Where did Noah's kids live</h2>
<p>In Genesis 7-8 the Bible describes the world population being reset by a flood that kills everyone but four men and their wives.  In chapter 9 they get out of the boat, in chapter 10 we get a genealogy, and then chapter 11 describes humanity thusly:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The whole earth was of one language and of one speech.  As they traveled from the east, they found a plain in the land of Shinar, and they lived there.  They said to one another, Come, lets make bricks, and burn them thoroughly. They had brick for stone, and they used tar for mortar.  They said, Come, lets build ourselves a city, and a tower whose top reaches to the sky, and lets make a name for ourselves, lest we be scattered abroad on the surface of the whole earth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Mankind didn't just default to living in cities like Jane Jacobs theorized, everyone on earth lived in a single city!  One city with apparently the economic surplus to fund a gigantic vanity project large enough to offend God.</p>
<p>So then God confuses their language, scatters them, and we enter the world of cities spread across the globe that Jane Jacobs describes in her book.</p>
<h2 id="it-s-a-good-book">It's a good book</h2>
<p>I quite enjoyed <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Economy-Cities-Jane-Jacobs/dp/039470584X/">The Economy Of Cities</a></em>.  Her theory of economies growing out of cities makes intuitive sense to me, and it seems perfectly in line with the biblical description of humanity's first millennium or so.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2024-05-01-contra-jane-jacobs.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2024-05-01-contra-jane-jacobs.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 19:00:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Merle Dean Kilgore]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Merle Dean Kilgore was born May 31, 1930.  He fought in the Army during the Korean war.  He was the trigger man on a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M1918_Browning_Automatic_Rifle">BAR</a> team.  Two assistant gunners on his team were killed.  The longest he went without changing his clothes or bathing in Korea was two weeks.</p>
<p>Stateside, he married Doris.  On a double date, she left her purse in his car so that he would have to bring it back and see her again.</p>
<p>He worked for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebraska_Public_Power_District">NPPD</a>.  In the early years, he and his young family lived in a trailer and moved around the state putting up the electric poles and lines.  He climbed a lot of utility poles.  On some vacations, especially the one to Canada, he would take his family driving country roads, looking for electric wires strung along the old glass electric insulators.  When he found one, he would climb the pole with the kit he kept in his trunk, replace the old insulator with a modern one, and add the glass insulator to his collection.</p>
<p><img src="./images/merle-nppd.jpg" alt="A blue glass insulator next to a business card of Merle D. Kilgore, District Manager, Nebraska Public Power District"></p>
<p>His father was an alcoholic.  Merle never touched alcohol.  His mother had an unusual level of financial knowledge for the time, and invested well.  She passed on financial knowledge to her children.  Merle put money into the stock market his whole career, lived modestly, and retired a millionaire at 59.  It's unlikely that any of his friends or neighbors knew how much money he had, since he never spent it on anything large and would never talk about it.</p>
<p>He was a worker.  After he retired, he and his wife volunteered for his church denomination, constructing church buildings in the south during winter and the north during summer. He was a useful carpenter and electrician.</p>
<p>Every spring when they got back, they would visit us a few days later.  He would ask my dad "so, what are we doing?"  He wanted a project to work on.  He helped build a porch, re-run ancient wires, finish our basement, hang sheetrock, insulate and put on a new roof.</p>
<p>When he wasn't working on a project, he watched war movies and the history channel from his la-z-boy.</p>
<p>After his stroke he couldn't really work on projects any more, which was obviously hard on him, though he never said anything about it.</p>
<p>He didn't talk much.  He was not a conversationalist.  He knew that I had silver and bitcoin, and would occasionally say something about it, but I was too dumb to hold an intelligent conversation with him about the financial markets that he was keeping track of.  I wish I had been capable of learning from him and keeping his high financial literacy from dying with him.</p>
<p>In 2018 he had a medical episode and several organs started to fail.  He was laying down on the living room carpet, unable to get up, but he and his wife decided to wait until the next morning to see if it was worth doing anything about.</p>
<p>In the hospital bed, a nurse described some mechanical options that could keep his kidneys and liver going a while longer, and he just shook his head.  He died about a week later in my parents' house.</p>
<p>He had two daughters.  I think he was fairly suspicious of my parents having so many kids, though I didn't hear him say anything about it, but by the time we started growing up I think he was on board.</p>
<p>Though he was a Christian, he didn't have the theory necessary to pass godliness on to his own children.  Thankfully, one of his daughters was converted at college and decided to have lots of kids.  He has more than a dozen great-grandkids in the world right now, and will probably end up with at least double that number.  He is on track to have a large number of descendants serving God at the end of history.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2024-05-13-merle-dean-kilgore.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2024-05-13-merle-dean-kilgore.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 15:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Communication culture]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>One of the most important things I've read is the post <em><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/ExssKjAaXEEYcnzPd/conversational-cultures-combat-vs-nurture">Conversational Cultures: Combat vs Nurture</a></em>.</p>
<p>A very short summary: what that post's author calls "combat culture", and what I will call "idea culture" is typified by people being willing to disagree with each other's ideas directly.  A conflict-avoidant culture, or "nurture culture" is typified by people affirming each other, and interpreting direct criticism or disagreement as an attack.</p>
<p>I would recommend reading the post, but I'm not writing this post to convince you to read it, more to get out some thoughts on the effective communication.</p>
<h2 id="my-stance-not-neutral">My stance: not neutral</h2>
<p>I've been practicing direct idea culture communication my whole career, and it seems obviously better than the conflict-avoidant style.</p>
<p>I want to work with people who care more about their work than they care about their ego, or being superficially aligned during a conversation.</p>
<p>We're here to figure out the truth  I don't really trust my ideas until someone I trust has tried to argue with them.  Working solo is a disadvantage because I don't get that check.  Working in a conflict-avoidant culture is the worst case, because even though I can tell my ideas to people, nobody will tell me if they disagree with me, and as a result I feel like nobody is listening to me.</p>
<p>I do disagree with the post's author when they say that countersignalling (the sort of friendly insulting that often happens between friends) has any place in an effective idea culture  productive arguments are about ideas and any hint of insulting, even as a joke, tends to get ego involved when it shouldn't be.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-effective-idea-culture">What is effective idea culture?</h2>
<p>Ineffective idea culture just looks like two people arguing without really listening to each other.  They might throw out some worthwhile ideas, but they're not seriously working to test their ideas out.</p>
<p>Mid-level idea culture might still look like an argument, but without the frustration.  The parties involved are iterating on their ideas during the argument.</p>
<p>The better the speakers are at idea culture arguments, the more clearly they will talk about the assertions being made, and the quicker they update their position when their counterparty makes a valid argument.</p>
<p>At higher levels it doesn't even look like an argument, it's just 2+ people having a discussion and quickly figuring out the Most Correct direction forward, as far as their human reason and experience are capable of.  <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/WB49uKgMkQRbKaHme/combat-vs-nurture-and-meta-contrarianism">This post</a> is a good description of the communication effectiveness spectrum.</p>
<h2 id="does-idea-culture-make-you-disagreeable">Does idea culture make you disagreeable?</h2>
<p>It shouldn't.  If you honestly care about finding the best way to do something, you should want other people who care to be willing to share their thoughts with you when they differ from yours.</p>
<p>The people I've worked with who cared the most about doing the best job possible, and were willing to argue with me when they thought I was wrong, have tended to be the ones I most wanted to be friends with.</p>
]]></description><link>https://joshduff.com/2024-07-18-communication-culture.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshduff.com/2024-07-18-communication-culture.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 14:44:39 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>